Guide to the Edward Lee Plumb Papers, 1856-1912
Department of Special Collections
Edward Lee Plumb Papers,
1856-1912
Special Collections M0149
Plumb, Edward Lee, 1827-1912.
4 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Ida Husted Harper, 1915, 1916.
Scope and Content
The Plumb collection consists of correspondence, cables, notes, reports, articles, drafts, clippings, maps, and some printed material from 1856 - 1912. Most of it falls between 1865 and 1881 though there are several gaps of months: October - December 1870 and July 1877. There is no correspondence for 1858, 1859, 1860, 1882, 1884 - 1888, 1890 - 1895, 1900 and 1901.
The papers are arranged chronologically showing the change and progression of Plumb's activities and interests. A partial index of correspondents and major subjects follows the list of contents. The most valuable and interesting subjects covered are: Mexican history from the French invasion to the beginning of Diaz's regime; United States diplomatic and commercial relations with Mexico, Cuba and Spain; history of the Cuban insurrection in the late 1860's to its culmination in the Spanish-American War; and American railroad and mining promotion in Mexico. It is rather strange that the preliminary steps for the construction of an International railroad are so well covered but there is almost no material on his eight year vice-presidency of the Mexican International Railroad.
The correspondents include many national and international figures: Mexican presidents; Mexican and American cabinet members, legislators, military men, journalists, diplomats and businessmen; Spanish military officials in Cuba; and businessmen and diplomats of several other nations active in Cuba and Mexico. There is one letter signed by Benito Juarez; 12 by Blas Balcarcel, Mexican Minister of the Interior, plus some signed documents; and 13 by Mexican legislator, Estanislao Cañedo. There are 102 letters from Plumb's friend, George Earl Church, from 1867 - 1907. Church was promoting a railroad and steamship line on the Amazon River and raising money in England. There are letters also from William R. Day (14), Hamilton Fish (3), Richard C. McCormick (15), William H. Seward (7), Philip H. Sheridan (4), and William T. Sherman (2). Diplomat John Watson Foster is represented by 38 letters and Henry C. Hall by 40. There are 15 letters by William Hunter of the State Department and 23 by Sebastian Lerdo de Tejada, president of Mexico. Among the businessmen with whom Plumb corresponded James S. Mackie is represented by 15 letters and Henry G. Marquand by 22. There are 67 letters between 1862 and 1898 from Matias Romero, Mexican diplomat and Plumb's personal friend.
Biographical Note
Edward Lee Plumb
1827, July 17 born in Gowanda, Erie Co., New York; son of Joseph and Caroline Robbins (Hale) Plumb; brother of Albert Hale Plumb, 1829 - 1907. received a business education and was apprenticed to a Hartford, Conn. mercantile house.
1849 went to California for several years.
1854 exploratory trip to Mexico, met Gen. Juan Alverez, obtained prospecting concession.
1855 interested New York businessmen in founding Mexican Pacific Coal and Iron Mining and Land Co.
1856 - 1857 surveying expedition across Central Mexico and returned to New York.
1861 - 1865 Mexico City - translater and interpretor with American Legation, other positions in Mexico and Washington, D.C.
1866 Secretary of Legation to Campbell Legation to Mexico.
1867 - 1868 Charge d'Affaires at Mexico.
1869, June - December Consul General at Havana, Cuba.
1871 - 1881 railroad promotion in Mexico and U.S. for International and Great Northern Railroad.
1881 sold rights in International concession.
1881 - 1889 vice-president of Mexican International Railroad Co.
1881, April 15 retired.
1912, April 16 died.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE 1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. 1856, May 10.New York Tax Cmmrs. to Mexican Pacific Coal & Iron Mining & Land Co., Ptd. notice
  - 2. 1856, Sep. 1.E.L. Plumb, Sec. Announcement for papers of a coming election for Trustees in Mex. Pac. Coal & Iron Mining & Land Co., A.N.S.
  - 3 & 4. 1856, Oct. 7.Geo. F. Allen to T[imothy] Cornwell., 2 A.N.S.
  - 5. 1856, Oct. 13.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Arrival in New Orleans, surveying party, routes from N.Y. to N.O., A.L.S. No. 1.
  - 6. 1856, Oct. 13 - 1857, June 16.Holograph list of ltrs. to Geo. F. Allen, showing dates, places of origin, etc.
  - 7. 1856, Oct. 19.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Arrival at Vera Cruz, 4 days by stage to Mexico City, Commenfort & the Church., A.L.S. No. 2.
  - 8. 1856, Oct. 20.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 2A.
  - 9. 1856, Oct. 20 - 1857, Feb. 16.List of letters recvd. by Plumb.
  - 10. 1856, Oct. 21.George F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 11. 1856, Oct. 21.T. Olcott receipt., A.D.S.
  - 12. 1856, Oct. 25.2 Bills of lading.
  - 13. 1856, Oct. 27.Thomas C. Garrett to Geo. F. Allen., A.N.S.
  - 14. 1856, Oct. 27.Thomas C. Garrett. Receipt., A.D.S.
  - 15. 1856, Oct. 27.John Tucker to Geo. F. Allen., A.N.S.
  - 16. 1856, Oct. 27.John Tucker receipt., A.D.S.
  - 17. 1856, Oct. 29.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 18. 1856, Oct. 29.Strickland Kneass to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S.
  - 19. 1856, Oct. 29.N.S. Strickland Kneass, Thomas C. Garrett, M. Dewskirk & John Tucker to Samuel J. Beals.
  - 20. 1856, Oct. 31.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Puebla taken over by Pronunciados, route of Dilligences changed, petitions to Mex. gov't., Mr. Lerde, Mexican stockholders, outbreaks or revolution., A.L.S. No. 3.
  - 21. 1856, Nov. 3.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 22. 1856, Nov. 4.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 23. 1856, Nov. 4.Express receipt.
  - 24. 1856, Nov. 6.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Surveying party delayed., A.L.S. No. 3A.
  - 25. 1856, Nov. 8.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. To buy animals, etc. at Orizaba, worried by political situation, sale of Church property., A.L.S. No. 4.
  - 26. 1856, Nov. 8.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. An apology., A.L.S. No. 4B.
  - 27. 1856, Nov. 9.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Official time extension, etc., A.L.S. No. 4A.
  - 28. 1856, Nov. 24.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 29. 1856, Nov. 29.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 30. 1856, Nov. 29.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Mentions [Ba____?] & Escauder & building RR from Vera Cruz to Mexico City., A.L.S. No. 5.
  - 31. 1856, Dec. 4.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 32. 1856, Dec. 5.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 6.
  - 33. 1856, Dec. 7.Clip from a Vera Cruz paper (Sp.) with holograph translation by Plumb? or [Henrique de Ravela?] to Samuel J. Beals &/or Geo. F. Allen.
  - 34. 1856, Dec. 9.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Arrival of Surveying Party (Manross, Poole, Bonner & Hamson), storms, Puebla uprising, robberies along the road, cabinet changes, mail, Prof. Whitney., A.L.S. No. 7.
  - 35. 1856, Dec. 8.List of letters missing.
  - 36. 1856, Dec. 19.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Money, RR from Vera Cruz., A.L.S. No. 9.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1857, Jan. - March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. [1857], Jan. 1.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Arrival in Mexico City, delay of baggage, political unrest, to interview Gen. Alvarez, iron ore specimens, magnetic ore, silver & lead, RR interests, meeting with Commonfort., A.L.S. No. 10.
  - 2. 1857, Jan. 1.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. ALlen. Financial letter showing expenses, etc., A.L.S. No. 10A.
  - 3. 1857, Jan. 1.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Report from Dec. 8, States of Guerrere, Michuacau & Colima--coal & iron mining rights were conceded to Henrique de Zavela, Carlos Maillard & Plumb & transferred to Co. Detailed description of country & conditions (economic, geographical, geological) comparison of estate laborers to southern slaves, Puebla shows signs of the recent battle, Cholula, etc. - route from Vera Cruz to Mexico City., A.L.S. No. 10B.
  - 4. 1857, Jan. 1.with hand-drawn map & profile of route from Vera Cruz to Mexico City. Henry W. Poole to Geo. F. Allen. Description & possibility of RR construction., A.L.S.
  - 5. 1857, Jan. 13.I. Commonfort to Geo. F. Allen. Transl. in hand of E.L. Plumb.
  - 6. 1857, Jan. 24.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Interview with Gen. & Don Diego Alvarez at Tasco, Pachuca mines. Real del Monte, mining methods, etc., A.L.S. No. 11A.
  - 7. 1857, Jan. 29.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 12.
  - 8. 1857, Jan. 31.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Political affairs, opinions on Mexican leaders, U.S. loan to Mexico., A.L.S. No. 11B.
  - 9. 1857, Feb. 1.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 11C.
  - 10. 1857, Feb. 4.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 13.
  - 11. 1857, Feb. 7.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 12. 1857, Feb. 10.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 14.
  - 13. 1857, Feb. 12.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 15.
  - 14. 1857, Feb. 13.Timothy Cornwell to Wm. W. Hanson., Copy of an A.L.S.
  - 15. 1857, Feb. 18.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 16.
  - 16. 1857, Feb. 19.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 17. 1857, Feb. 20.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 17.
  - 18. 1857, Feb. 26.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 19. 1857, Feb. 28.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 20. 1857, Feb.E.L. Plumb. Stmt. showing mean cost of reducing a mountain of ore at the Real de Monte Cos, reduction establishments in 1854., A.D.S.
  - 21. 1857, Feb.J.D. W[hitney]. Advice & opinion re: Mexican operations., A.D.S.
  - 22. 1857, Mar. 18.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Acct. of surveying expedition to headwaters of the Rio Mescala., A.L.S. No. 18.
  - 23. 1857, Mar. 23.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 24. 1857, Mar. 23.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 18A.
  - 25. 1857, Mar. 24.A sales slip.
  - 26. 1857, Mar. 30.A.C. Bagley to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1857, April - (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. 1857, Apr. 13.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 2. 1857, Apr. 21.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 3. 1857, Apr. 27.D.B. Van Brunt to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 4. 1857, May 27.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen. Copper & iron district, mineral findings., A.L.S. No. 21.
  - 5. 1857, June 16.E.L. Plumb to Geo. F. Allen., A.L.S. No. 22.
  - 6. 1857, June 18.E.L. Plumb to Minister Lerdo. Preliminary report of findings of survey party & request for futher time extension., A.D.S.
  - 7. 1857, July 8.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 8 & 9. 1857, July 14.Geo. F, Allen to Timothy Cornwell., 2 A.N.S.
  - 10. 1857, Aug. 3.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 11. 1857, Aug. 5.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 12. 1857, Aug. 12.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 13. 1857, Aug. 14.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 14. 1857, Aug. 15.Wm. R. Hanson to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 15. 1857, Aug. 19.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 16. 1857, Aug. 21.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 17. 1857, Aug. 21.Wm. R. Hanson to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 18. 1857, Sep. 3.Mex. Pac. Coal & Iron Mining & Land Co. to Henrique de Zavela., A.Df.
  - 19. 1857, Sep. 25.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 20. 1857, Sep. 24.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., L.S.
  - 21. 1857, Sep. 28.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 22. 1857, Sep. 28.Mex. Pac. Coal & Iron Mining & Land Co. to Strickland Kneass et al. New Charter., A.L.
  - 23. 1857, Sep. 29.Thomas C. Garnett to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 24. 1857, Sep. 29.Strickland Kneass to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 25. 1857, Sep. 30.Geo. F. Allen to [Timothy Cornwell]., A.N.S.
  - 26. 1857, Sep. 30.Archibald Robertson to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 27. 1857, Oct. 6.Wm. R. Hanson to Timothy Cornwell., A.L.S.
  - 28. 1857, Oct. 8.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 29. 1857, Oct. 14.Henry W. Poole to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 30. 1857, Oct. 17.James Eddy to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 31. 1857, Oct. 29.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 32. 1857, Nov. 20.Henry Ward Poole to [Geo. F. Allen]. Description of map., A.L.S.
  - 33. 1857, Dec. 5.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 34. 1857, Dec. 19.Geo. F. Allen to Timothy Cornwell., A.N.S.
  - 35. [1857?].Geo. G. Bellows. Opinion., A.D.S.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1861 - 1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. [1861].L. Timothy Cornwell to Ches. Robinson. Copy by Plumb with explanatory note.
  - 2. 1861, Mar. 31.Thomas Corwin to E.L. Plumb. State Dept. apptmt., legation to Mex., A.L.S.
  - 3. 1861, Sep.Note on Mexican foreign debt.
  - 4. 1861, Dec. 23.E.L. Plumb to U.S. Bill for services with by Thomas Corwin., A.N.S. D.S.
  - 5. 1862, Feb. 10.E.L. Plumb to Charles Sumner. Copy of a memo re U.S.-Mexico relations., A.Df.S. & copy.
  - 6. 1862, Mar. 29.E.L. Plumb to Duncan, Sherman & Co. France's claims on Mexican national debt, Mexican situation since 1857., A.L.S. (copy).
  - 7. 1862, Apr. 11.Wm. H. Seward to E.L. Plumb. Apptmt. as special courier to carry President's ratification of Postal & Extradition Treaties to U.S. Minister in Mexico City. Instructions., D.S.
  - 8. 1862, Apr. 16.Gideon Wells to W. W. McKean., A.L.S. (copy).
  - 9. 1862, Apr. 17.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 10. 1862, Apr. 17.F.W. Seward to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 11. 1862, May 15.Thomas Corwin to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 12. 1862, May 21.Thomas Corwin to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 13. 1862, Nov. 26.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Accuses Seward of being pro-French., A.L.S.
  - 14. 1862, Nov. 27.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Seward recalls a dispatch., A.L.S.
  - 15. 1863, Jan. 14.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Occupation of Jalapa boy the French., A.L.S.
  - 16. 1863, Jan. 19.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 17. 1863, Mar. 7.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Assassination of Maj. Bernardi., A.L.S.
  - 18. 1863, Apr. 12.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 19. 1863, May 24.J. Edgar Thomson to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 20. 1863, June 20.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. His return to Mexico, loss of Puebla, evacuation of Mexico City., A.L.S.
  - 21. 1863, July 14.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. To join the army., A.L.S.
  - 22. 1863, July 16.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 23. 1863, Aug. 19.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Description of Diaz & army., A.L.S.
  - 24. 1863, Aug. 24.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 25. 1863, Oct. 28.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Back in Washington [as Minister?]., A.L.S.
  - 26. 1863, Oct. 30.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 27. 1863, Nov. 11.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 28. 1863, Nov. 18.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 29. 1864, Feb. 17.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 30. 1864, Feb. 23.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 31. 1864, Feb. 27.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 32. 1864, Mar. 8.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 33. 1864, Mar. 15.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 34. 1864, July 15.M. Romero to Plumb. Raid on Washington & Baltimore., A.L.S.
  - 35. 1864, Oct. 20.M. Romero to Plumb. Arrival of Gen. Doblado., A.L.S.
  - 36. 1864, Oct. 30.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero. Possibilities of a war with France., A.L.S.
  - 37. 1864, Nov. 23.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 38. 1864, Nov. 26.M. Romero to Plumb., A.L.S.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1865, January - May (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1. 1865, Jan. 23.Treaty of Union & Alliance between the States of America parties thereto for their mutual defence., D. (copy).
  - 2. 1865, Jan. 23.Treaty - For the preservation of Peace among the States of America, Parties thereto., D. (copy).
  - 3. 1865, Mar. 4.Tratado de Correos. Spanish copy of postal treaty., Doc. (copy).
  - 4 & 5. 1865, Mar. 10.Copies of Doc. Treaty of Commerce and Navigation - one by Plumb, one a draft or translation from Spanish., 2 Eng. copies
  - 6. 1865, May 2.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 7 & 8. 1865, May 2.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S. & different version (a copy).
  - 9. 1865, May 3.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., Letterpress A.L.S.
  - 10. 1865, May 4.Letterpress & df. on Mexican loan. E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., A.L.S.
  - 11. [1865, May 4?].Letterpress Doc. - Mexican loan.
  - 12. 1865, May 5.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 13. 1865, May 6.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 14. 1865, May 8.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., Letterpress A.L.S.
  - 15. 1865, May 9.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., Letterpress A.L.S.
  - 16. 1865, May 9.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 17. 1865, May 10.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., Letterpress A.L.S.
  - 18. 1865, May 10.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb, A.L.S.
  - 19. 1865, May 11.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., L-P A.L.S.
  - 20. 1865, May 11.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 21. 1865, May 17.E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., L-P A.L.S.
  - 22. 1865, May 18.three plans upon the respective bases for loan. E.L. Plumb to M. Romero., L-P A.L.S.
  - 23. 1865, May 18.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1865, August - October & n.d. 1865 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1. 1865, Aug. 10.E. de[Courcillon] to Hayne & Co. Report on results of investigating trip to Mexico re: an Express business. Port business, roads & railroads, modes of transportation, translation of decree from Maxmilian, etc., A.D.S.
  - 2-4. 1865, Sep. 27.E.L. Plumb. An article The United States, France and Mexico or France, Mexico and the United States., A.D.S. & 2 dfs.
  - 5. 1865, Oct.W.A. Corbiere to unknown. Sugar plantation in southern part of State of Vera Cruz business venture proposed., A.L.S.
  - 6. [1865?].[E.L. Plumb?]. The United States and France. Our diplomatic position upon the Mexican question., A. Df. of article.
  - 7. [1865?].[E.L. Plumb?]. No title. Changing character of French-Mexican war., A. Df. of article
  - 8. [1865?].[E.L. Plumb?]. Complicity of Belgium in the Invasion of Mexico., A. Df. of article
  - 9. [1865?]. A Joint Resolution for the protection of Citizens of the United States in the matter of Public Loans of the Republic of Mexico., A. Df. of Doc.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1866 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1. 1866, Jan. 22.Louis Napoleon. Copied by [E.L. Plumb?]. A translation with comments., Copy of Speech.
  - 2. 1866, May 7.E.L. Plumb to Alexander Duncan. Mexican affairs & debts, British bonds., A.L.S.
  - 3. 1866, May 8.Alexander Duncan to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 4. 1866, May 27.[E.L. Plumb? to Alexander Duncan., A.L.S.
  - 5. 1866, May 27.[E.L. Plumb? to [James Gordon] Bennett re: an article on Mexico., A.L.
  - 6. 1866, May 28.E.L. Plumb to unknown. (Author of above-mentioned article)., A.L.S.
  - 7. 1866, Nov. 2.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. In Spanish., A.L.S. & cvr.
  - 7a. 1866, Nov. 3.E.L. Plumb to Matias Romero. Investigation of claims by Treadwell & Co. against Mexican government. Vega's purchase of ____ in S.F. Ochoa bonds., A.L.S.
  - 8. 1866, Nov. 5 - Dec. 29.E.L. Plumb Diary. Apptd. Sec. of Legation to Mexico, voyage, Havanna, Mexico, Texas, New Orleans., A.D.
  - 9. 1866, Nov. 7.William H. Seward to E.L. Plumb. Apptmt. cmm. & instructions., L.S.
  - 10. 1866, Nov. 10.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward., A.L.S.
  - 11. 1866, Dec. 7.E.L. Plumb to R.S. Chew., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1866, Dec. 24.H. Sturm to Lerdo de Tojada. Accounts against govt., Copy of letter
  - 13. 1866, Dec. 24.H. Sturm to M. Romero., Copy of letter
  - 14. 1866, Dec. 26.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward., A. Tel. S. (copy).
  - 15 & 16. [1866?].[E.L. Plumb]. 2 similar short biographies of Benito Juarez., 2 A.D.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1867, January - April (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1. 1867, Jan. 3.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward., A.L.S.
  - 2. 1867, Jan. 11.S.M.[Bowman] to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 3. 1867, Jan. 11.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward. Extract of a letter from Marshall. Locating various generals and Juarez., A.L.S.
  - 4. 1867, Jan. 18.Lewis G. Brown to E.L. Plumb. Movements of Mexican army., A.L.S.
  - 5. 1867, Jan. 19.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward. Mr. Lane., A.L.S.
  - 6. 1867, Jan. 30.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 7. 1867, Jan. 30.William H. Seward to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 8. 1867, Feb. 2.E.E. Dunbar to E.L. Plumb. Failure of Campbell mission, impeachment matter., A.L.S.
  - 9. 1867, Feb. 8.James S. Maekie to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 10. 1867, Feb. 11.Franklin Chase to E.L. Plumb. War news & rumers., A.L.S.
  - 11. 1867, Feb. 17.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1867, Feb. 25.Isaac Moses to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 13. 1867, Mar. 1.William H. Seward to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 14. 1867, Mar. 3.George E. Church to E.L. Plumb. Course of war, etc., complaints of U.S. residents in Mexico., A.L.S.
  - 15. 1867, Mar. 7.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward. Arrival of French warships at Vera Cruz., A.L.S.
  - 16. 1867, Mar. 13.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward with transl. of Maximilians order to Mexican (his) Army - Feb. 17, puts himself in command; transl. Representation & Protest addressed by Foreign Representatives resident in Mexico to Maximilian, Feb. 4., A.L.S.
  - 17. 1867, Mar. 14.E.H. [Saulener] to E.L. Plumb. Embarkation of French troops from Vera Cruz., A.L.S.
  - 18. 1867, Mar. 18.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward., A.L.S.
  - 19. 1867, Mar. 18.H.D.J. Pratt to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 20. 1867, Mar. 19.William H. Seward to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 21. 1867, Mar. 23.William H. Seward to E.L. Plumb., L.S.
  - 22. 1867, Mar. 24.[E.L. Plumb] to William H. Seward., A.L. (df.)
  - 23. 1867, Mar. 29.[E.L. Plumb] to William H. Seward., A.L.S. (df.)
  - 24. 1867, Mar. 30.E.H. Saulnier to E.L. Plumb. Siege of Vera Cruz by Liberals., A.L.S.
  - 25. 1867, Apr. 2.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb. Siege of Queretaro., A.L.S.
  - 26. 1867, Apr. 3.H.D.J. Pratt to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 27. 1867, Apr. 4.E. Yorke to E.L. Plumb., A.N.S.
  - 28. 1867, Apr. 9.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward., Tel.
  - 29. 1867, Apr. 9.[E.L.Plumb] to William H. Seward, A.L.
  - 30. 1867, Apr. 12.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 31. 1867, Apr. 24.Edward Downey to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 32. 1867, Apr. 28.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
- CORRESPONDENCE 1867, May - August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1. 1867, May 5.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 2. 1867, May 9.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward. British Honduras (Belize) -- lands, immigration., A.L.S.
  - 3. 1867, May 10.Edward Downey to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 4. 1867, May 10.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward. Belize, Mexico & Guatamala., A.L.S.
  - 5. 1867, May 21.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb. Transmitting official letter of May 15.... Fall of Queretaro, capture of Maximilian, Mejia, Castillo & Miramon., Tel.
  - 6. 1867, May 28.Edward E. Bunbar to E.L. Plumb. U.S. opinion against execution of Maximilian., A.L.S.
  - 7. 1867, May 30.Charley D. Porten., A.L.S.
  - 8. 1867, June 1.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward re: [execution?] & Campbell's message., A.L.S.
  - 9. 1867, June 4.Edward F. Palmer to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 10. 1867, June 11.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb. May 29 Maximilian's court martial convened., Tel.
  - 11. 1867, June 13.Allan McLane to E.L. Plumb. Steamship business on west coast of Mexico., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1867, June 13.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb., A.N.S.
  - 13. 1867, June 18.Philip H. Sheridan to E.L. Plumb. Maximilian's trial postponed., A.N.S.
  - 14. 1867, [June 18].Philip H. Sheridan to E.L. Plumb. Campbell's registration., A.L.S.
  - 15. 1867, June 19.Ignacio Mariscal to E.L. Plumb., A.L.S.
  - 16. 1867, June 25.E.H. Saulnier to E.L. Plumb. Maximilian shot June 19, June 20 Mexico City surrendered to Diaz., A.L.S.
  - 17. 1867, June 26.E.L. Plumb to William H. Seward. Acquisition of Alaska, eventual acquisition of British America, and Mexico., A.L.S.
  - 18. 1867, June 27.M.B. Marshall to E.L. Plumb. Admiration for Maximilian., A.L.S.
  - 19. 1867, June 28.M. Romero to E.L. Plumb. Mrs. Juarez & family on way to New Orleans., A.L.S.
  - 20. 1867, June 29.S. Philip H. Sheridan to U.S. Grant (copy to Plumb of cypher telegram). Maximilian's execution June 19, refusal to deliever body?, Tel.